Hello, welcome back
to Lam Rim.
We're starting
episode number 9.
I like to call it
"A Visit to the Center of the Sun".  We've been
talking
about something that's big enough
and powerful enough,
it's like a nuclear bomb used
to clean ketchup off your blouse or something.
And I'm not exaggerating.
I want you to think like this.
Imagine...
So today in the United States, it's
Independence Day.
I'm speaking on
Independence Day,
and many times we go on
a picnic with our family.
It's the middle of summer.
And American children will eat
hot dogs or hamburgers
and put a lot of ketchup on them,
and a tiny, tiny squirt of ketchup will
fall here.
Imagine that to clean it,
the mother sends the shirt
or blouse into the center of the sun...
[inaudible]
...to clean a little bit
of ketchup, red ketchup.
I know it sounds like
a strange image,
but I'd like you to try to think about it.  I would like you to
try to think about that.  I do
n't know what to compare it to.
Yes, I don't know.
Just put a small thing
in the center of the sun, okay?
So let's visit the center of the sun
today.
And I'm happy to announce
that we've just reached the third
and final section of the Lam Rim.
The steps on the path
to enlightenment.
From this moment on
we are about to move on
to the activities of a bodhisattva.
We are about to start thinking
and acting like a bodhisattva,
who is the person of greatest ability.
(KYES BU CHEN PO)
Which means a person
of great ability.
Those of you, especially those
of you who have followed this Lam Rim
for the past ten years,
should be super happy
that we have survived
and that I have survived to reach
the final part.
We're in the final part.
It's the last third.  Now...
those mathematicians among you
should be thinking: "Okay, Geshela,
"you just said we have 25%
to go.
So why is that
the last third?"
And the answer is that
Pabongka Rinpoche's treatise
on the last two days of Lam Rim
is too short.
His presentation of meditation
and his presentation of seeing emptiness,
the last two of the six perfections,
isn't very long.
And I don't know what happened. I
mean, sometimes it's... it's
like...
if the sponsor came up to him and said,
"We're going to run out of food in two days."  "It's
almost over."
It's possible...
maybe it's a mystical message from Tara,
or maybe, I don't know, maybe he had another appointment
in another city.
But if you ask me,
Pabongka Rinpoche made the last two parts
shorter
because Je Tsongkhapa had already covered them
in his great Lam Rim,
"The Great Book on the Steps on the Path
to Enlightenment," the Lam Rim Chenmo.
Tsongkhapa did such a great job
that I think I can see Pabongka Rinpoche
saying,
"You know, guys, there's not much reason for me to
teach this part
because Tsongkhapa already taught it,
and he did it extraordinarily well."
There are many stories about Tsongkhapa
writing those last two parts,
and I'm so happy that we're going
to do them together.
So we're going to finish this
Lam Rim series
with amazing teachings on meditation
and emptiness.
So that's why this part
on the steps on the path for people
who have bodhichitta, for Bodhisattvas,
isn't as long
as it could have been.
So here we go.
Let's...  Read the Tibetan.
(GSUM PA SKYES BU CHEN PO'I LAM GYI RIM
PAR BLO SBYANG BA LA)
Let us train our hearts
in the steps on the path
for people of great ability.
People who are bodhisattvas.
(THEG CHEN GYI 'JUG SGO SEMS BSKYED KHO NAR BSTAN PA PHAN YON DANG BCAS PA)
It says that we are going to cover this,
the lifestyle of a bodhisattva, we
will cover it in three different steps.
Number one.
(THEG CHEN GYI 'JUG SGO)
If you want to enter the path of the bodhisattva,
there is only one way
to get there.
And that is by attaining
a certain state of mind.
If you want to become enlightened, if you want to have
the opportunity to become enlightened,
if you want to have the opportunity
to help the world, there is
only one way.
You have to attain bodhichitta.
You have to get this desire
to attain enlightenment
so that you can help countless beings.
Now, I want to talk about countless.
The  Bodhichitta is directed
toward countless living beings. It's
not directed toward every person in your city
or every person in your country
or every person
on this planet.
Forget that;
if we want to send the virus to the center of the sun,
if we want to visit the center of the sun,
forget this idea
that we're working
for every person on this planet. We're
not.
Forget this idea that we're trying
to help
every fish and every bird
and every
animal that walks
on land—
we're not, that's not the point.
We're covering the entire universe.
We're deciding today
that I would like to help
every living being in the universe.
Every tiny virus, every bacterium.
Every whale.
Every human in the universe.
So, go outside at night in Sedona,
or outside of Sedona—Rim Rock is better—
and look at the stars and try to imagine.
Then, first, you can't practice
the lifestyle of a bodhisattva
if you don't expand your mind toward that...
toward that goal.
And if you really experience it,
what  It takes some practice.
If you truly send your mind,
if you are truly able to attain
bodhichitta,
then the things you have to do
in this world are nothing. There is
nothing.
It is insignificant.
Helping all the people
in this world is nothing. It
is easy.
(PHAN YON DANG BCAS PA) means:
I want to tell you the benefits of thinking like this.
That is the first step.
(BYANG CHUB TU SEMS BSKYED PA'I TSUL)
Second step.
How do you arrive at this great breakthrough?
Mental breakthrough?
How do you perceive the entire universe
and all beings in it?
And then develop love for them.
Is it possible?
That is the second step.
Third step.
(SEMS BSKYED NAS SPYOD PA LA SLOB TSUL LO)
Let's learn how to act
like a bodhisattva.
Once you have this hope
of becoming a bodhisattva,
well then, practically,
what am I supposed to do?
How do I spend the hours of my day
if  Do I want to act like a bodhisattva?
What should I do?
What will my agenda be?
Well. Here's the first one.
(DANG PO NI, DE LTAR SKYES BU CHUNG
'BRING GI SKABS SU)
(SKABS SU NGES 'BYUNG GI BSAM
PAS KUN NAS BSLANGS)
So now that we've gone through the steps
on the path
for people of lesser
and middle ability,
at least you should have this feeling
that...
really, life is pain,
really, this life is a problem.
The virus makes it obvious.
But it's always been like this. There's
always been a virus
called death.
This virus is the new one.
It's much smaller.
But at least now we're all
thinking about it.
(LHAG PA'I BSLAB PA GSUM LA 'BAD PAS)
Then, we were supposed to work
on the three extraordinary trainings.
Treat other people well.
Spend time in meditation.
And then try to see that things
don't come from your own side.
('BAD PAS RANG GCIG PUS  (THAR BA'I GO
'PHANG THOB TZAM)
(DANG 'KHOR BA LAS LDOG TZAM 'BYUNG)
You can reach nirvana by yourself
and you can get out of the Wheel of Life.
If you practice with these attitudes, you can,
it is possible. We
already taught you this, we already finished
with that.
(DE TZAM GYIS MI CHOG)
But I don't want you to stop there. I do
n't want you to stop there.
I want you to... There is much more
to do. There is
much more to do.
Don't stop there.
(SPANG BYA THAMS CAD MA SPANGS)
If you stick to what I taught you
so far, you
will not cleanse your heart
of all the impure things
that are there.
(THOB BYA YON TAN THAMS CAD KYANG
YONGS SU MA RDZOGS PAS)
And you have not attained
all the higher spiritual qualities
that you could have attained.
(MA RDZOGS PAS)
Therefore
(RANG DON DANG, GZHAN  (DON YANG NYI
TSE BA LAS MI 'BYUNG)
(NYI TSE BA)
There's a very discouraging word here.
There's a very sad word here.
It says, you can work on those paths I've
taught you so far, you can
work on all those meditations I've
taught you so far,
but the amount of good you will do
for yourself and others
is only a small amount
of what you need to do.
(NYI TSE BA)
means:
it's only a small amount
of what you should be doing.
And, by the way, the most common use
of that word is...
it's the Tibetan word for hell
on earth.
Which is very strange.
So there's a big hell that people
can go to.
But I always think of a person who had
a car accident and the car exploded
and they're engulfed in flames.
In the scriptures, that's called
(NYI TSI BA'I DMYAL BA),
a little piece of hell on this plane.
On this plane of reality.
And so this word (NYI TSI BA)
means just a small piece.
And here  He says, "Do you want to help yourself
and do you want to help other people?
Everything I've taught you so far for
10 years
(NYI TSI BA)
is only a small fraction
of what you could be doing, and now
we're ready to start with the serious stuff."
"Well, Geshe-la,
why did we spend 10 years
doing the (NYI TSI BA),
the little things?
Why didn't we just go
to the higher things?"
Because small things are a ladder
that helps you reach higher things.  You ca
n't reach the highest things
unless you do the other two parts.
Unless you practice all the steps
of Lam Rim
in their correct order,
you will never reach the
bodhisattva part.
So, you can't say you don't
want them.
Part of the bodhisattva lifestyle
is mastering the lower path
that helped you get there.
And you never reject them.  You
simply grow from them.
(MI 'BYUNG ZHING SLAR THEG CHEN
LA GZHI NAS 'JUG DGOS LA)
This is an idea in Buddhism,
that as soon as you are ready,
and as soon as you have
the preparation,
you should jump straight into the
bodhisattva lifestyle, because...
if you don't, you're going to have to do it again
anyway.
So, sooner or later
you have to get here.
Maybe this lifetime will take you.
Perhaps it will be later in this life.
People approach me from time to time
and say,
"I'm going to take a break
from this Dharma.
I feel like I need to take
a break."
"There are other things I
have to do now.
"I have a big project at work,"
or: "I have family things going on
and I need to take a break."
I said that to one of my teachers in India, I
remember.
45 years ago.
And I said, "I need to take a break."
And he looked at me and said,
"Yes, that's fine."  But you will return.
"You will return because there is nowhere else to
go.
You will return."
You will return to this because you need to return to this.
Life will bring you back here.
Because that's how life is.
You need the Lam Rim.
Life will always bring you back to the Lam Rim, unless you die.
And it will still bring you back
to it later.
(SLAR) means you have to come back again.
(SLAR THEG CHEN LA GZHI NAS)
(GZHI NAS) means you're going to waste a lot of time
if you have to go back to it.
It's better to do it now
rather than come back to it later.
The next image here
is a little bit of something I want to do with you
in this episode, episode nine.
I call it "A Visit to the Center of the Sun."
So in this image, I
tried to find an image...
that's close to what it feels like to have
bodhichitta.
So this image looks a little...
we were saying, Seiji, Tim, and I,
that it's a little "new agey."
It looks like it was painted in Sedona, Arizona.
It feels a little new age,
but let me say something.
If
you ever get bodhichitta,
it will feel...
this image is very  Close.
This image is kind of close.
Can you put it down?
Just for a minute?
This image isn't crazy,
and it's not some kind of hippie thing.
When you reach bodhichitta, real bodhichitta,
it feels very much like this.
So maybe you'd like to make a copy of this image. We
already paid for it.
So you could use it at home.
You could have it at home.
You could have an image like that.
Maybe put it as your phone's screensaver.
It's pretty close to what it feels like to
get bodhichitta.
So I'd like to take you
on a little trip,
just for fun,
maybe five minutes.
We're going to go over what it feels like when you...
when you reach real bodhichitta
for the first time.
So we're not talking about estimated...
what do you call it? Partial bodhichitta.
Or trying to feel like you have bodhichitta.
We're going to talk about the real thing.
The day you see emptiness directly
and experience bodhichitta directly,
we're going to go over it because it's lucky.
And it's an atomic bomb.
If you keep working on it,
if you keep working on this...
feeling, how it feels,
if you keep listening to this part,
it will help destroy the virus.
I think it will help destroy the virus.
It's like a nuclear weapon.
And the virus is like a ketchup stain.
So here we go.
Let's try to imagine for five minutes
what it feels like to attain bodhichitta.
Here we go.
Take ten slow breaths.
Concentrate on the exhales, long exhales,
don't worry about the inhales, your body will breathe.
So please imagine that you have just seen
emptiness directly.
And that you have just stepped out of that
direct perception,
and you are back in what we might call normal meditation, which doesn't yet exist in the world.
You are in a deep state of meditation, you
are still on your cushion.
Your eyes are closed.
Then, suddenly, before your mind comes the image
of your mother. It is your mother.
A perfect image of your mother.
A living image. It
really is your mother.
Perhaps as you best remember her.
She looks like this right now. She
is
She's looking into your eyes.
Even though it feels like she's
at the forefront of your mind, she's
looking into your eyes.
With great love and also a sense
of need.
She needs help deeply.
She's in trouble
somehow.
Like she's jumping off the Titanic or something,
and she's looking at you with those eyes...
She's saying, "I need you,
I need help."
And then you say out loud
in your heart,
"Don't worry, Mom,
I'll take care of you."
"And I will be strong enough to take care of you. You
don't need to worry.
I will have the power to help you, and I will, I
promise."
And then his image fades
from your mind
and suddenly there is the image
of your father.
And you're looking at your father.
And she has that same look in her eyes.
He's a little expectant.  But also fearful.
So he sees you as:
"Can you help me?
Things are getting tough in life,
life is hard now."
Then you say, "Dad, don't worry.
I'm on it.
I'm studying Lam Rim."
"I'm studying a lot
about emptiness.
And I actually know I'll have the tools
to help you soon."
"So don't worry. I'm on it. I'm
taking care of it.
And please don't... you don't have to be afraid."  You do
n't have to worry.
"I know what to do
and I'm doing it.
Everything will be alright, so do
n't worry."
And then, perhaps another person close
to you, your wife or your husband
or your children,
one of your children,
their image appears
before your mind.
Just her face.
And they're also looking at you like,
"Can you help me?
Things are bad, things are
really bad."
"Things are mortal, there's no other hope.
Can you help me?"
And you say, "I've got it covered,
I'm taking care of it.
I can do it."
"I will have enough power to take care
of you.
" "You really don't have to worry."
"I know what's going on.
I know your situation. I
know what this life is like."
"I've got it sorted and I'll be taking
complete care of you. You do
n't have to worry."  You
really don't have to worry.  "
I'll take care of it."
And then that face fades, and then you can
begin to see the faces of the people you know.
Close people, close family.
Uncles, aunts.
Brothers, sisters.
Nephews, nieces.
One by one, you bring them in and comfort them.
And you say, "I truly will take care of it."  "
You'll have nothing to worry about."
And in this way, we end up with
all the people we know.
All the people you've met
in your life.
Then you start working
with all the people you have
n't met and with all the people
in this world.
You start with your own neighborhood.
Go out to the city, the whole city.
And you know, it's not like you can cover
the whole world. But,
take one person here
and take one person there.
Take them to the shores of this continent you
live on.
Cover everyone.
And then go beyond.
To other continents.
And in this way, we cover all the people
in this world.
Just sitting here.
And then you can start with the animals
in this world, with the fish,
and I'm not talking about types of animals.
I'm talking about...
helping
each animal individually.
Each one is looking at you.
Each one is waiting.
Each one is afraid.
Each one receives its personal guarantee.
"I'm on it."   "
I'll take care of that."
Just imagine going for every creature,
tiny creatures at the bottom of the sea.
Tiny creatures
in your bloodstream.
Meeting each one.
Talking to them.
And when you're done with every living being
in this world,
we'll start
on the next world. I do
n't know where the next world is. I do
n't know if it's Alpha Centauri.
Maybe it's many light-years away
from here.
Go there...
and start doing the same meditation
for every person in that world.
And in this way, we cover every world
in the entire universe.
And the karma of meeting one by one,
every one of the seven billion
human beings,
and trillions of other creatures
on one planet,
and then covering as many planets as there are.
Countless planets.
Covering every being there,
that's bodhichitta.
That's the direct experience
of bodhichitta.
So please, in this episode,
if you can just feel it. You do
n't have to worry about yourself. You don't have to worry
about your family. You
really don't have to worry
about your country.
And you don't have  than worrying about a world
covered in a virus.
Those are small things.
We'll take care of them,
by the way.
We're working on a much
bigger project.
We're committing to helping
an entire universe.
Countless billions of beings.
Countless billions of animals
and other creatures.
And we have that capacity.
You have that capacity. I
pray that you will attain it
in this lifetime. I pray
that you will open it
in this lifetime.
Your mind already has the capacity to touch
every living being
and promise them that you will take care of them.
So, the purpose of this Lam Rim,
the purpose of this retreat,
is like traveling to the center of the sun.
Think about every living being.
Countless living beings in a
limitless universe.
Find them one by one.
Make a promise to them one by one.
That's what happens during the first
direct experience of bodhichitta. It
really happens.
That's what it feels like
.
If you keep visualizing it, it
will help it happen. It
really does.
So, it's up to you
if you want it to happen.
If you really want to be a true
Bodhisattva,
so practice... practice this visualization
once or twice a day.
Just when you have a few minutes.
Just imagine.
In your imagination. Okay?
And it will help to bring it about.
And you will attain bodhichitta.
So something like the virus,
for that kind of bodhisattva, the virus
isn't a very big thing. It's
a very small thing.
It's a very small thing.
Making money.
Making a living.
Feeding your family.
Finding an apartment.
These are incredibly small things. They're
nothing.
Your mind is like...
your heart is like the center of the sun.
And some... I don't know...
a few cookies or...
a few Cokes in the center of the sun, it does
n't matter. It's
not a big thing.
Go for the big!
Everything else becomes small.
And everything else becomes comfortable.
Simple.
That's bodhichitta.
Okay. See you in the next episode.
Episode 10.